<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>daiyi</title>
    <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="/blog/rss2.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    
    <description>thoughts and ideas and essays by daiyi; unrefined brain-to-internet pipe; public journaling</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 03:49:56 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>http://hexo.io/</generator>
    
    <item>
      <title>What am I reading? (February 2017)</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/28/What-am-I-reading-February-2017/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/28/What-am-I-reading-February-2017/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:16:59 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;I didn’t get through much this month because I’m reading Modern Operating Systems in slow motion and Seveneves took forever, but here are the books I read in February! Part of an &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/categories/what-am-I-reading&quot;&gt;ongoing series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn’t get through much this month because I’m reading Modern Operating Systems in slow motion and Seveneves took forever, but here are the books I read in February! Part of an <a href="/blog/categories/what-am-I-reading">ongoing series</a>.</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<h3 id="The-Brief-and-Wondrous-Life-of-Oscar-Wao-Junot-Diaz"><a href="#The-Brief-and-Wondrous-Life-of-Oscar-Wao-Junot-Diaz" class="headerlink" title="The Brief and Wondrous Life of Oscar Wao - Junot Díaz"></a>The Brief and Wondrous Life of Oscar Wao - Junot Díaz</h3><h4 id="fiction-really-good"><a href="#fiction-really-good" class="headerlink" title="fiction | really good!"></a>fiction | really good!</h4><p>tldr: READ IT IT IS GOOD. HOly shit this book was turned up to 11. Completely unapologetically crass and carnal narration, chaotic bouncing around to different pov and people until the narrator materialises within the story themself. Intense, headstrong and tragic characters charging directly into anguish. Maybe because I was raised under a rock in upper middle class white suburbia but this book was bleeding a vibe and culture and a completely different way of experiencing america/the world than I’ve ever seen or heard and I liked that so much. And maybe the most surprising part that I didn’t bargain for but was amazed by, a stern talking-to about my ignorance of and catchup with a particularly brutal part of Dominican history, dictatorship under the Trujillo cult of personality. 1000/10 it’s a good dog read this book!!</p>
<p><em>How to read this book</em>: with wikipedia on hand for historic sidetrips!</p>
<h3 id="Seveneves-Neal-Stephenson"><a href="#Seveneves-Neal-Stephenson" class="headerlink" title="Seveneves - Neal Stephenson"></a>Seveneves - Neal Stephenson</h3><h4 id="speculative-sci-fi-I-liked-it"><a href="#speculative-sci-fi-I-liked-it" class="headerlink" title="speculative sci-fi | I liked it"></a>speculative sci-fi | I liked it</h4><p>All in all middle-of-the-road Stephenson; it’s a single threaded plotline with fast paced edge-tickling action cut with long, more boring analysis/gratuitous description of random pieces of technology.</p>
<p>I can see some people being super into the future-tech deep dives but I just came here for the philosophical thought experiments about future human societies. The thought experiments are super interesting!</p>
<p>Some of the book is maneuvering the situation as to set up the various thought experiments so it does give off a bit of feeling contrived, and more softer scifi. I recognised this trade-off and felt pretty forgiving. I’d recommend this book if you like Stephenson, but if you’re new to Stephenson you should probably read Snow Crash or something instead!</p>
<p><em>How to read this book</em>: play along with the thought experiments and have a discussion buddy as you read; reading this book definitely felt more satisfying when I had someone to talk/rant about the ideas in it with.</p>
<p>Also DON’T READ the back cover summary (and I’m not even a person who cares about plot twists). It’s more motivating get through such a long book if you have no idea what’s going on :D</p>
<h3 id="Nonviolent-Communication-Marshall-B-Rosenberg"><a href="#Nonviolent-Communication-Marshall-B-Rosenberg" class="headerlink" title="Nonviolent Communication - Marshall B. Rosenberg"></a>Nonviolent Communication - Marshall B. Rosenberg</h3><h4 id="non-fic-I’d-recommend-it"><a href="#non-fic-I’d-recommend-it" class="headerlink" title="non-fic | I’d recommend it"></a>non-fic | I’d recommend it</h4><p>I like how this book formalises a lot of ideas I have floating around in my head about how to meet people where they are at emotionally, expressing your own needs in terms of actionable items, etc. (a whole ‘nother topic for another time). I like comparing it against <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/769016.How_to_Talk_So_Kids_Will_Listen_Listen_So_Kids_Will_Talk" target="_blank" rel="external">How to Talk So Kids Will Listen and Listen So Kids Will Talk</a>, which has similar axioms but angles it more towards parenting/interacting with children (which is really powerful for communicating with adults sometimes).</p>
<p>I’ve started teaching again this month and have gotten some nice reminders that putting these ideas to practice is a muscle I must constantly flex (like how I am starting to injure my back while climbing because I’m out of bouldering shape, oops).</p>
<p>Incidentally, I’ve also had a couple of encounters with adults that really put me in my place in terms of my wild expectations for how I can make my life better from self-improvement. (If people are super mad and feel entitled to making you miserable, it takes a better person than me to not regress to profuse apology in order to make them go away and stop yelling at me. Fuck that noise. I’m tired of people telling me I need to be kinder and more understanding and more gentle. That’s the case for the kids I teach, with my family, my friends, my peers and colleagues. If someone approaches you with the attitude that you are lesser than them sometimes there’s nothing you can do to convince them to respect and consider you as an equal. If a rando doesn’t want to be reasoned with FUCK them, that is super not ok and I will not be cornered into emotional prostration.)</p>
<p><em>How to read this book</em>: I find it really helpful to take bullet notes as I’m reading. I’ve discovered that I really need to jot down specific examples of phrases and words when reading these types of books, because the examples tend to illustrate ideas better than describing them in abstract.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/28/What-am-I-reading-February-2017/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>notes from a civic hackathon</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/28/notes-from-a-civic-hackathon/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/28/notes-from-a-civic-hackathon/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 11:34:24 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hacktheban.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Hack The Ban&lt;/a&gt; was an anomaly among tech events, with a focus on b
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.hacktheban.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">Hack The Ban</a> was an anomaly among tech events, with a focus on building relationships between local activist groups and the local tech community. Though the event was formed in response to the immigration executive order, organisations representing immigration rights/marginalised communities have existed for a very long time. Startup folk have an impulse to prop up new solutions when they see problems, which is great in many cases, but sometimes it is also worth considering joining forces with organisations that have intimate ties with and understanding of the community they are serving, a decade of work, and a diversity of skillsets and backgrounds and experiences.</p>
<p>Because it was a single day event, there was no sleep deprivation necessary, and due to the motivation/theme, the usual competitive factor that makes ordinary hackathons unappealing to some types of people (me!) was noticeably absent. Everyone wins at a civic hackathon (:</p>
<h3 id="mingling"><a href="#mingling" class="headerlink" title="mingling"></a>mingling</h3><p>In the last few months I’ve been waving my hands in the dark around the question: “how can I be an effective activist? what do non-profits need from technologists?” After a morning welcome speech and warm coffee of happiness, there was a sort of non-profit club fair, where technologists got to ask questions and hear from organisers about their tech needs and the needs of the community.</p>
<p><img src="hack-the-ban.jpg" alt="hack the ban"></p>
<p>Some thoughts and observations:</p>
<ul>
<li>woah there’s no dedicated developer at a lot of these orgs. so it’s important that any tech setup (website, electronic donations page, email list) is very simple, readily safe/secure, and requires very little training</li>
<li>many orgs seem to feel a need for <em>something</em> (e.g. infographics, pamphlets, data visualisations) but can’t exactly articulate what it is. it is our job as technologists to extract their needs from listening to their goals, in a way that reminds me of being a tech consultant.</li>
<li>many things are done by hand (e.g. managing mailing lists). a no-background-knowledge-assumed kit/guide to automating these tasks could free up a lot of time/resources (but be careful of investment and maintenance time-cost)</li>
<li>with orgs that serve specific communities, <u>multilingual accessibility</u> is very important.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="hacking"><a href="#hacking" class="headerlink" title="hacking"></a>hacking</h3><p>Most of the participants came as individuals, and self-organised into groups that paired with the non-profits. I ended up among a wide range of experience and skillsets, and it was super cool watching everyone come together and the more senior folks take leadership, ask focused questions, and delegate. Thoughts from the hacking portion:</p>
<ul>
<li>project management and delegation is SO. IMPORTANT. good management is a productivity multiplier!</li>
<li>it’s great to be a generalist who can jump into things and figure out how existing stuff works</li>
<li>consultant skills are very useful – trying to decide tech stack, experience with working with different tools, pros/cons of various options</li>
<li>someone brought their graphics tablet, which was an excellent idea. I’m 100% throwing my wacom into my backpack next time for emergency wireframing/design prototyping</li>
<li>as with an ordinary hackathon, have project templates, communication channels, and staging environments ready to save precious time (but unlike an ordinary hackathon, it’s uncertain what existing systems we’d come across)</li>
</ul>
<p>I left feeling optimistic, with a reminder to be patient – it can be slow to find your footing within a space, be it industry or volunteering, because fundamentally it is about human relationships, which takes time. Slow is ok. I’m doing what I can.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/28/notes-from-a-civic-hackathon/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What am I reading? (January 2017)</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/13/What-am-I-reading-January-2017/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/13/What-am-I-reading-January-2017/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 01:21:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I love browsing other peoples’ reading lists!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>I love browsing other peoples’ reading lists!</strong><br><a id="more"></a></p>
<p>My culture tells me that reading books is something a respectable intellectual should do a lot of, but it’s been pretty far down the list of priorities ever since I had to seriously come to terms with the fact that sustaining a regular sleep and exercise schedule is key to holding off crippling depression. Well now I’m on a nomadic sabatical and there is time for books again!</p>
<p>When I was back home over winter holiday, my brother was dragging his face through a book club book he hated, with the explanation that he found fulfillment in figuring out exactly what it was about a book that he hated. So I started a spreadsheet about my <em>feelings</em> of all the things I’ve been reading, because I too love dissecting my feelings and analysing my reactions to a precise degree yet still having very little command of my emotional muscles and tendons (a duality of theory/execution understood by anyone who has tried learning handstands or the butterfly stroke).</p>
<p>Here I’ll clean up and publish the monthly spreadsheet book reviews for your browsing pleasure!</p>
<!-- more -->
<h3 id="The-Fifth-Season-N-K-Jemisin"><a href="#The-Fifth-Season-N-K-Jemisin" class="headerlink" title="The Fifth Season - N.K Jemisin"></a>The Fifth Season - N.K Jemisin</h3><h4 id="fic-scific-10-10"><a href="#fic-scific-10-10" class="headerlink" title="fic, scific | 10/10"></a>fic, scific | 10/10</h4><p><em>The Fifth Season</em> is fucking fabulous, the best scifi/fantasy I’ve read in a really long time. The worldbuilding is stunning and thorough, depicting tribalism and societal manipulation in nuanced and real ways that is Too Real, you don’t get sat down with an explanation of anything that’s going on so there’s a lot of discovery (including the fact that the book is ACTUALLY SCIFI) through narrative, and every realisation feels intentional and well-placed. Queer/poly/trans representation is presented without cringe-worthy tokenness, and in fact is really good. Pacing is amazing and doesn’t let up. Graphic narrative that is so strong I had to read out of the corner of my eyes during particularly intense scenes. The way abusive emotional relationships (between family members, a racial group vs society, between mentor and student) are depicted are so tragic and multifaceted that you aren’t yelling at characters for doing the Wrong Thing, you’re angonising about how horrible and confusing being a person is. The writing does a bit of the high fantasy air to it (maybe that’s why I thought it was fantasy at first) that usually annoys me but I stopped being epsilon annoyed by it as soon as the story picked up. READ. THIS BOOK.</p>
<p>(also whenever I see a non-male author going by initials I get flashbacks of JK Rowling being advised that people wouldn’t read Harry Potter with a feminine name on the cover.)</p>
<h3 id="The-Obelisk-Gate-N-K-Jemisin"><a href="#The-Obelisk-Gate-N-K-Jemisin" class="headerlink" title="The Obelisk Gate - N.K Jemisin"></a>The Obelisk Gate - N.K Jemisin</h3><h4 id="fic-scific-read-this-if-you-liked-the-last-one"><a href="#fic-scific-read-this-if-you-liked-the-last-one" class="headerlink" title="fic, scific | read this if you liked the last one"></a>fic, scific | read this if you liked the last one</h4><p>The second book in the series, continuing from before. It doesn’t win your heart with novelty like the first book, but it takes more steps into scifi and provides explanations and continues at breakneck pace. I liked it as a second book, and the third one is coming out later this year \o/</p>
<h3 id="Modern-Operating-Systems-Tanenbaum"><a href="#Modern-Operating-Systems-Tanenbaum" class="headerlink" title="Modern Operating Systems (Tanenbaum)"></a>Modern Operating Systems (Tanenbaum)</h3><h4 id="technical-computer-science-good-for-unrefined-systems-ragamuffins-me"><a href="#technical-computer-science-good-for-unrefined-systems-ragamuffins-me" class="headerlink" title="technical, computer science | good for unrefined systems ragamuffins (me)"></a>technical, computer science | good for unrefined systems ragamuffins (me)</h4><p>I’m reading along as my sister takes her major’s operating system’s course. This book gets personal with touches of snark and is what feels like a pretty approachable introduction to OS stuff. Weirdly enough it’s patching up the gaps of knowledge I have acquired through my backalley self-education on distributed systems as a bystander to the container wars last year.</p>
<h3 id="Limits-to-Growth"><a href="#Limits-to-Growth" class="headerlink" title="Limits to Growth"></a>Limits to Growth</h3><h4 id="economy-systems-good-ideas-probs-not-worth-the-entire-read-for-most"><a href="#economy-systems-good-ideas-probs-not-worth-the-entire-read-for-most" class="headerlink" title="economy, systems | good ideas, probs not worth the entire read for most"></a>economy, systems | good ideas, probs not worth the entire read for most</h4><p>I am about 40% through this book. It seems to be a textbook used in some undergrad courses, about the world as systems and I noticed the terminology being similar to that of <em>Thinking in Systems</em> (which I also read 40% of, last year) – because Donella Meadows is an author on both books! It introduces a lot of interesting, abstract ideas on political and social sustainability with regards to growth, and the pitfalls of how politicians and voters think about growth and rates of growth. I got stuck at the part where the book goes into detail about water, land, and other resource consumption facts, which, while interesting and worthwhile, are probably more suited for a research project than my vague goal of trying to understand the big picture of why the world is going to shit. I’m planning to return to this book next month, skipping that section and getting through the rest of the ideas (maybe post my notes?)</p>
<h3 id="Training-for-the-New-Alpinism-Freedom-of-the-Hills"><a href="#Training-for-the-New-Alpinism-Freedom-of-the-Hills" class="headerlink" title="Training for the New Alpinism; Freedom of the Hills"></a>Training for the New Alpinism; Freedom of the Hills</h3><h4 id="Apparently-Freedom-of-the-Hills-is-the-Mountaineering-bible"><a href="#Apparently-Freedom-of-the-Hills-is-the-Mountaineering-bible" class="headerlink" title="Apparently Freedom of the Hills is the Mountaineering bible"></a>Apparently Freedom of the Hills is the Mountaineering bible</h4><p>Mountaineering books that I started reading when I moved to the northeast and thought I would do a lot of mountaineering this season! That didn’t really happen for a variety of reasons, but that’s okay I’m going to be so prepared next year! Also I can’t believe no one told me how good Freedom of the Hills is as an introduction to technical mountaineering. Jeez. It’s just great. Super technical and with pictures!</p>
<h3 id="Ice-World"><a href="#Ice-World" class="headerlink" title="Ice World"></a>Ice World</h3><h4 id="technical-ice-climbing-it’s-like-a-story-and-also-a-manual"><a href="#technical-ice-climbing-it’s-like-a-story-and-also-a-manual" class="headerlink" title="technical, ice climbing | it’s like a story and also a manual"></a>technical, ice climbing | it’s like a story and also a manual</h4><p>This is an older technical ice climbing book that I started to read from my gym’s little climbing library when I thought I would do ice climbing this season :P Same story as above. I like how it starts with a bunch of stories, and has a friendly narrative-approach to teaching, including a section where the author instructs the finer points of glacier traversal by documenting the process of <em>teaching his wife through a hands-on expedition</em>.</p>
<h3 id="On-The-Road-Jack-Kerouac"><a href="#On-The-Road-Jack-Kerouac" class="headerlink" title="On The Road - Jack Kerouac"></a>On The Road - Jack Kerouac</h3><h4 id="semi-autobiographical-travel-counterculture-DNF"><a href="#semi-autobiographical-travel-counterculture-DNF" class="headerlink" title="semi-autobiographical, travel, counterculture | DNF"></a>semi-autobiographical, travel, counterculture | DNF</h4><p>I didn’t finish this book. I couldn’t get into Jack Kerouac’s prose or the story. Which is super sad, because I’m a iconoclast hippie dirtbag like Kerouac and I keep seeing good quotes from his writing and praise for this work and I really wanted to like it! At first pass it should have everything I like a lot: stories from the road, weird hitchhiking stuff, the windy, uncommited flow of consciousness style that I love in Didion and post-modernists like DFW. I really disliked the people the protag surrounds himself with and feel frustrated that I have to spend time with these characters, who feel kind of worthless and kind of like the type of trash I have long cut out of my own life, sexist attitudes and dishonesty and fuck-all laziness and apathy and self-pitiful ennui. I just don’t need to wade through the maturity level of the social landscape of this time in the author’s life I guess.</p>
<h3 id="The-Golden-Compass-Philip-Pullman"><a href="#The-Golden-Compass-Philip-Pullman" class="headerlink" title="The Golden Compass - Philip Pullman"></a>The Golden Compass - Philip Pullman</h3><h4 id="YA-fic-childhood-reread-exceeds-expectations-recollection"><a href="#YA-fic-childhood-reread-exceeds-expectations-recollection" class="headerlink" title="YA fic, childhood reread | exceeds expectations/recollection"></a>YA fic, childhood reread | exceeds expectations/recollection</h4><p>The subject of childhood rereads came up when I was hanging out with elementary/middle school friends over winter holiday, and I picked The Golden Compass to revist.</p>
<p>HOW is this a children’s novel?? The protag being a prepubescent child is the only thing children about this book. It deals with loads of mature themes (balance of power between church/state, love between a semi-immortal and humans), geography and culture comes at you really fast and without much explanation, plays on alt-history with renamings of abstract concepts (science is called philosophy or theology, electricity is called anbaric) that are hard to catch without an early high school education and without understanding of which it would seem a lot of the magic and meaning in the story might be lost?? I certainly don’t remember catching ANY of this in my first readthrough (in middle school). In fact I have retained almost nothing from the first readthrough except that there were daemons and armoured bears, probably because it all went completely over my head but I liked bears and wanted a daemon. It 1000% feels like a young adult book written for adults. Even more so than stuff like The Hunger Games, which doesn’t feel nearly as nuanced! Hunger Games feels so straightforward and civil compared to this world, jesus.</p>
<p>My one gripe is that, once I step back a little from the action and world-building, the plot appears very deus ex machina. Pretty much all conflict is overcome by a third party that miraculously swoops in with exactly the correct skillset to perfectly conduct a rescue. This is forgivable, given that it IS a children’s novel so it’s supposed to read like a story/tale rather than realistic rendition of how the world works, and that the action and characters are really exciting and distract from the plot drop-ins. Also the characters really pop and are super fun. Great book, great re-read, the opposite of disappointment!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2017/02/13/What-am-I-reading-January-2017/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Say it out loud to make it real. Promise to not use your powers for evil.</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/12/13/Say-it-out-loud-to-make-it-real-Promise-to-not-use-your-powers-for-evil/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/12/13/Say-it-out-loud-to-make-it-real-Promise-to-not-use-your-powers-for-evil/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 04:20:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever criticised leadership in any way, you know how hard it can be to move a muscle against an invisible wall,
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve ever criticised leadership in any way, you know how hard it can be to move a muscle against an invisible wall,<a id="more"></a> endlessly high and dispassionately immense. When something seems wrong enough that you, a single tiny person in a big world machine, feel moved to action, you start doubting yourself. If this is so horrible, why hasn’t someone else already done something about it? Surely this would never be allowed to happen? When you open your mouth to tentatively voice your concerns everyone is suspiciously quick to violently agree. They already know it. Dysfunction is obvious. Action is hard. I’m a good person. I needed the experience. I needed the money. It was a good career move that couldn’t have come a moment sooner. All valid and important and so it is crucial that we act as an uncompromising unit.</p>
<p>Because tech companies won’t come out and say it, individuals in tech are signing <a href="http://neveragain.tech" target="_blank" rel="external">a pledge</a> that’s circulating the tech-o-sphere to remain diligent against misuse of user information and ethically questionable corporate maneuvers in light of recent political developments:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We have educated ourselves on the history of threats like these, and on the roles that technology and technologists played in carrying them out. We see how <a href="http://www.ibmandtheholocaust.com" target="_blank" rel="external">IBM collaborated to digitize and streamline the Holocaust</a>, contributing to the deaths of six million Jews and millions of others.</p>
<p><cite><a href="http://neveragain.tech" target="_blank" rel="external">http://neveragain.tech</a></cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok I have already learned something new today.</p>
<p>Friends, you are overwhelmingly like me: young, passionate, concerned. If you don’t want to commit yourself to a what is almost definitely a public watchlist, you don’t have to. Write it in your diary. Tell your friend over brunch. Do any small thing to make it real.</p>
<p>I’m back in California for a sweet interlude and I can feel my brain moving as I scrape up my ankles and bloody my knuckles on cliffs and eat with friends. They give me love and make me feel safe. They’re a time capsule of my old life. I start to forget why I left Berlin. I’m questioning my decision to move to New York in the middle of winter. I start to feel silly and overemotional and unnecessarily cynical. I open a bunch of tabs to plan my next trip and window shop for gear. But I can’t forget because after I woke up November 12 and held out a whole half day before breaking down in tears, I wrote to sort out my confusion. This is the curse of chronic journalers. I don’t think I’ve ever felt as American as I did when I was crying thousands of miles away from home about America.</p>
<p>I am torn by the selfish desire to remain uninvolved and alive and the selfish desire to feel like I’m doing something useful. Maybe you are too. <em>Capture that feeling.</em> Make it persistent in your own way. Memorialise it. Use it to set a breakpoint for when you see something that makes you feel uneasy. It’s hard. It’s impossible. It’s okay to seek safety. But if you can, build up your muscle memory so that when the time comes your rationalisation won’t impede your instinct.</p>
<p>–</p>
<p><em>(relatedly, holler if you know of a project or people that need software hands. I’m not in a particular hurry to find income, I mostly want to appease my selfish desire to feel helpful, so consider this a desperate cry for help rather than a marketing opportunity. I know throwing money at organisations is the best way to make progress but hey, I got the time. Email <a href="http://daiyi.co">me</a>.)</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/12/13/Say-it-out-loud-to-make-it-real-Promise-to-not-use-your-powers-for-evil/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>signaling in tech is some fucked up shit</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/30/Signaling-in-tech-is-some-fucked-up-shit/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/30/Signaling-in-tech-is-some-fucked-up-shit/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 08:07:57 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I am exactly as cool as I was before I started writing clojure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>I am exactly as cool as I was before I started writing clojure.</strong><br><a id="more"></a></p>
<p>I’ve had a short, short life as a programmer and I’ve spent a lot of it making websites. Back in the day (as in a couple years ago) when I told other software people I’m a web developer, I got treated like shit. I was a lower class of coder because I wasn’t “solving cool problems” because making web sites is easy. It was sad and confusing to receive unjustified hatred but I loved the internet and I thought it’s pretty neat to make things that everyone can use and I like the visual component to my projects so I’d just go secretly cry in the bathroom (cool tricked I learned in college) like an ordinary functioning adult.</p>
<p>Somewhere along the way there was a massive rebranding so then I was doing literally the same things but now I’m a Frontend Engineer or UI Engineer. Occasionally I’d still get trashed by other coders but that’s ok, I even get to sit with the other software folks sometimes!</p>
<p>I found web and design communities where people do good web things and encourage each other to be better. It’s cool. Love is out there.</p>
<p>A month or two ago I started picking up clojure. I don’t know why other people learn new programming languages, but I didn’t know anything about clojure’s rich history and I wasn’t chasing the Beauty of Lisp or the superior mindset it would teach me or hoping to harness the performance or flexibility. I had no fucking clue about any of that. I’d just started reading <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp" target="_blank" rel="external">SICP</a> because I missed computer science after bumping around in industryland, and it seemed trivial to swap scheme for clojure while doing the exercises in the book and end up being competent at a language I heard rumours that people use sometimes rather than a language I knew people used never.</p>
<p>And I liked it! It was my first lisp and yeah coming from javascript and python I liked the quaint syntax, and the way everything is all about these couple of data structures, and thinking functionally and non-mutably (word salad word salad). More significantly, I’d just left my previous job pretty much hating programming, and clojure was reminding me about why I like programming, and that was lovely. I noticed it was possible to use clojure to make UIs via clojurescript and figured it’d be a cool way to connect these two interests and go full circle.</p>
<p>I mentioned to some people I was learning clojure. Everyone was <em>super</em> into this. People started telling me I was really cool. I noticed people making all these wildly positive assumptions about my programming ability despite not having read a single line of code I’ve written ever. I instantly get elevated to a respect-worthy status for free and maybe for people who are used to being treated well that’s not a big deal, but coming from being treated like trash after telling people I am a web person the contrast was super intense and really obvious. I felt like I stumbled into a mystery bizarro-verse where you get dignity by default. It was SO WEIRD.</p>
<p>It’s fucked up that being interested in this random programming language, not even for the reasons the fangirls love it, suddenly caused everyone to start being nice to me when I’m in fact the same trash can that I’ve been all along. Coming upon the Correct Signal by accident made it all feel extra wrong and extra strange, like I killed a man and wore his skin for a suit and suddenly inherited all the achievements ever made in that body.</p>
<p>I know railing against signaling is itself a signal that I am a naive member of society who has yet to smash out of my youthful optimism chrysalis into the apathetic reality machine. Signaling is going to be there no matter what, because human nature. All I can do is reflect in stupid amazement at this experience and compel you to treat others with respect by default. Seriously.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/30/Signaling-in-tech-is-some-fucked-up-shit/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>everything I do feels so trite</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/13/everything-I-do-feels-so-trite/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/13/everything-I-do-feels-so-trite/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 09:53:57 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;civic guilt, cultural privilege, and a flurry of other lovely thoughts in the wake of USA election 2016.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have never seen so many people publicly acknowledge being brought to tears.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>civic guilt, cultural privilege, and a flurry of other lovely thoughts in the wake of USA election 2016.</strong></p>
<p>I have never seen so many people publicly acknowledge being brought to tears. <a id="more"></a> Well, here’s me: I’m on European time so I woke up to full hysteria. My gay black American roommate was freaking out since 07:00 CEST as the election day was drawing to a close stateside. I made it all the way to late afternoon before I started receiving celebratory messages in the family chat. I burst into tears and tyler held me as I shook with sobs, no words.</p>
<h3 id="immobilising-guilt"><a href="#immobilising-guilt" class="headerlink" title="immobilising guilt"></a>immobilising guilt</h3><p>I’m dreading my trip to South America in January after being excited about it for years. It just feels silly now. Everything feels silly. I read but then I put down my books. I write code and it just seems wrong that I’m doing that instead of … something else? Even writing this feels like a comical waste of time even though putting words to feelings is helping me work through this confusion.</p>
<h3 id="responsibility"><a href="#responsibility" class="headerlink" title="responsibility"></a>responsibility</h3><p>I think of my lovely friend, Ping, an excellent human who from my arm’s length vantage point seems to be constantly weighted by guilt that he hasn’t saved all humans by now. And then there is my friend d, who is an upstanding person and thoughtful conversationalist, patron of the arts and appreciator/contributor to fine engineering. He dreams nothing more than to purchase a plot of land as remote as possible on which to build his stronghold against the fluctuations of a confused society. He wants to bring his friends there so he has excellent company.</p>
<p>These are my reference points. And so it comes down to the maddening question of balance, finding the right point along the spectrum of how much fucks to give. Too many fucks, and you’re in constant agony while carrying the emotional burden of all humans (and maybe animals too, if you’re into that). Not enough fucks and you’ve denounced the very society on which you’ve scaffolded your comfort, success, and happiness.</p>
<p>We want to do something, anything that will alleviate the horrible feeling of helplessness. We ask, how do we help? what can we do?</p>
<h3 id="uncomfortable-answers"><a href="#uncomfortable-answers" class="headerlink" title="uncomfortable answers"></a>uncomfortable answers</h3><p>It doesn’t feel satisfying but throwing money at orgs that need it is crucial: ACLU, planned parenthood, EFF. But without getting your hands in you don’t have the delicious sensation of making a difference. And what about all these skills I have? Shouldn’t someone out there need some code or something?</p>
<h3 id="please-stop-telling-me-to-empathise"><a href="#please-stop-telling-me-to-empathise" class="headerlink" title="please stop telling me to empathise"></a>please stop telling me to empathise</h3><p>I sincerely wish I could see over the internet wall into the other side. I want to believe trump supporters are saying to each other, <em>wow these people are angry, but maybe we can try to understand them. Go talk to a Hillary supporter. Don’t know any? Well that’s your problem. I guess it’s reasonable that they worry more about the safety of themselves and their loved ones than they worry about our economic anxiety.</em></p>
<p>I really really hope someone out there is saying that the way like-minded folk to myself are saying the inverse to me.</p>
<p>The underlying assumption there that everyone had a blissful upbring where they peacefully inherited their values from their family is almost insulting. Some people had to look elsewhere for their moral frameworks, and going back is a mental health death wish.</p>
<p>I already understand them, thanks. And that’s more than they’ve done for me.</p>
<p>So now that we understand each other, then what?</p>
<h3 id="I-was-young-the-last-time-we-voted-in-a-non-Obama-president-Was-it-like-this"><a href="#I-was-young-the-last-time-we-voted-in-a-non-Obama-president-Was-it-like-this" class="headerlink" title="I was young the last time we voted in a non-Obama president. Was it like this?"></a>I was young the last time we voted in a non-Obama president. Was it like this?</h3><p>Were people telling each other to stay safe? Were they sharing tips on how to intercept public acts of aggression towards marginalised people? I hear talk of stockpiling medication that they owe their life to the way I imagine people talk about stockpiling guns in case of gun control.</p>
<p>People say they are <em>shocked</em> that this happened not because it’s actually surprising that people are willing to overlook (embrace?) racism, xenophobia, etc in favour of their own livelihoods, their jobs, a promise of the continuity of their familiar way of life. They’re shocked because it was a physical blow of disbelief from the <em>formalisation</em> of the divide in priorities that we already knew all about. Shit got real.</p>
<h3 id="the-environment-is-fucked-and-we’re-going-to-be-responsible-for-affecting-all-humans"><a href="#the-environment-is-fucked-and-we’re-going-to-be-responsible-for-affecting-all-humans" class="headerlink" title="the environment is fucked and we’re going to be responsible for affecting all humans"></a>the environment is fucked and we’re going to be responsible for affecting all humans</h3><p>Here’s to hoping we hit the singularity and gain ultimate understanding as a global hivemind before we manage to destroy each other, so that the jokes rolling out of my mouth in a sad coping mechanism don’t feel as trite as writing all of this in the time I could have used to apply for socially responsible software jobs. I’ll speak up when I can. I’ll fight if I’m able. I will escape if the worst happens (I’m not going to pretend tyler and I didn’t talk about contingency plans). I will find a balance between paying back for the good things my society has given me and appreciating the things that make me happy about this life and I must do this asap.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/13/everything-I-do-feels-so-trite/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A week on the Swiss Via Alpina</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/08/A-week-on-the-Swiss-Via-Alpina/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/08/A-week-on-the-Swiss-Via-Alpina/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/2016/11/08/A-week-on-the-Swiss-Via-Alpina/daiyi-hikin.png&quot; alt=&quot;daiyi unable to face the camera due to overwhelming beauty of alps&quot; title=&quot;daiyi unable to face the camera due to overwhelming beauty of alps&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a week walking the Via Alpina trail in Switzerland from late September to early October 2016.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/blog/2016/11/08/A-week-on-the-Swiss-Via-Alpina/daiyi-hikin.png" alt="daiyi unable to face the camera due to overwhelming beauty of alps" title="daiyi unable to face the camera due to overwhelming beauty of alps">
<p>I spent a week walking the Via Alpina trail in Switzerland from late September to early October 2016.<a id="more"></a> I inevitably collect cool thoughts and cool photos when I hike for 8 hours a day and have always wanted to write a trip report, but motivation/time is eaten when I rejoin society and work/school. I have neither of those responsibilities right now! Posts will be serialised under <a href="/blog/tags/via-alpina">Via Alpina</a>.</p>
<h3 id="when-you-go-to-a-fancy-modern-country-to-sleep-on-the-side-of-the-road"><a href="#when-you-go-to-a-fancy-modern-country-to-sleep-on-the-side-of-the-road" class="headerlink" title="when you go to a fancy modern country to sleep on the side of the road"></a>when you go to a fancy modern country to sleep on the side of the road</h3><p>I love that the alps are super accessible (grandmas and dogs and babies all over the places, rails running out of every town to the top of every pass), and people go there specifically to enjoy the European charm and convenience of mountain cabins/huts. So of course I ignored all the modern comforts the country had to offer, wild camping and hitchhiking instead. I took one train, two hours from Zurich to my arbitrarily selected trailhead in Engelberg, which was a fresh and smooth experience that, like all the other Swiss things, put the quality of their counterparts in other countries to shame, but also used all my food budget for the month. It was lovely for being the only train I pay for my entire stay in Europe.</p>
<p>The trail was really developed and full of cows and people, so we got pretty creative about finding places to sleep! (Ominous foreshadowing music)</p>
<h3 id="Contradictions"><a href="#Contradictions" class="headerlink" title="Contradictions"></a>Contradictions</h3><ul>
<li>I’m on a fairly tight budget, but Switzerland is notoriously expensive.</li>
<li>I like packing ultralight but I was flying to a wedding right and needed nice clothes ✨</li>
</ul>
<p>Even with cautionary tales of $20 McD from friends who visited earlier in the summer, I was unable to handle how crazy Switzerland prices were, even with my recent past life in the luxurious San Francisco tech startup reality sphere. We brought our food in from Germany, an excellent country with reasonable grocery bills and an appreciation for tasty dehydrated meals (in the US you have to go to a sport store for that).</p>
<h3 id="Here-are-some-ways-I-prepared-for-the-trip-because-I-sometimes-get-questions-about-how-I-travel-o"><a href="#Here-are-some-ways-I-prepared-for-the-trip-because-I-sometimes-get-questions-about-how-I-travel-o" class="headerlink" title="Here are some ways I prepared for the trip, because I sometimes get questions about how I travel \o/"></a>Here are some ways I prepared for the trip, because I sometimes get questions about how I travel \o/</h3><p>Basically I like to collect a ton of info so I can put off deciding on specifics for as long as possible. This is the kind of thinking that both leads me to sleeping on the side of the road but also in a secluded magical fairy wonderland (both happened).</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://activityworkshop.net/hiking/alpinepassroute" target="_blank" rel="external">activity workshop .net</a>, an oddly-named website which provided kickass gps maps and elevation reliefs and info about the towns along the Swiss via alpina.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://osmand.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">OSM-AND</a> and <a href="http://maps.me/en/" target="_blank" rel="external">Maps.me</a> android apps, which I used to read gps coordinates/trails from above. Both superior to google maps for (my style of) travel because of</p>
<ul>
<li>excellent offline support</li>
<li>easy bookmarking/note-taking that exports to standard formats</li>
<li>you can search for bathrooms omg</li>
<li>more data for hiking trail/natural features (eg mountain peaks)  </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><p>I also highly recommend the <a href="http://osmand.net/features?id=contour-lines-plugin" target="_blank" rel="external">OSM-AND topo plugin</a> for a super awesome hiking experience :D</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://hitchwiki.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">Hitchwiki</a> – a wiki and map contributed by hitchhikers for hitchhikers!</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://getpocket.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Pocket</a>, which I used to offline cache aforementioned resources.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/08/A-week-on-the-Swiss-Via-Alpina/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I went to IndieWebCamp</title>
      <link>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/08/I-went-to-IndieWebCamp/</link>
      <guid>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/08/I-went-to-IndieWebCamp/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 06:30:04 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;or, justification for satisfying annual urge to completely revamp web presence.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am inspired by the promises of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/why&quot;&gt;Indie Web&lt;/a&gt;. Owning your data, cool. A single source of truth to your content and identity, nice. Possibility of sinking countless hours into configuring your own corner of the internet, ok you got me there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m hearing some rattling in my internet social spheres about how content silos are making the internet more homogeneous, forcing you to conform and contort your thoughts into prescribed formatting, that force of nature that causes experts in their fields to blast out 50-part tweetstorms that should be written in an article instead. Hey you sound exactly like the indiewebcamp people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/&quot;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;. They’re nice, too (:&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>or, justification for satisfying annual urge to completely revamp web presence.</strong></p>
<p>I am inspired by the promises of an <a href="https://indieweb.org/why" target="_blank" rel="external">Indie Web</a>. Owning your data, cool. A single source of truth to your content and identity, nice. Possibility of sinking countless hours into configuring your own corner of the internet, ok you got me there.</p>
<p>I’m hearing some rattling in my internet social spheres about how content silos are making the internet more homogeneous, forcing you to conform and contort your thoughts into prescribed formatting, that force of nature that causes experts in their fields to blast out 50-part tweetstorms that should be written in an article instead. Hey you sound exactly like the indiewebcamp people!</p>
<p>Go <a href="https://indieweb.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">check it out</a>. They’re nice, too (:</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<h3 id="personal-minutia"><a href="#personal-minutia" class="headerlink" title="personal minutia"></a>personal minutia</h3><p>This is going to be a static site because it is just a blog; if I am generating enough content to need a database behind it I should probably be getting paid for it. Fun fact: in middle school, my diary was a series of .txt files.</p>
<p>I know everyone and github is really into jekyll, but I decided to use <a href="https://hexo.io/" target="_blank" rel="external">hexo</a> to generate my static site for the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’m a node developer (bring on the hate) who is too lazy to install ruby stuff on my computer.</li>
<li>hexo’s developer community is surprisingly full of chinese people. I am forced to face my illiteracy and read a lot of chinese. It will be good practice :D</li>
</ul>
<p>Speaking of which, I’m pretty surprised I don’t encounter a lot more chinese developers on the internet, seeing as how there’s a lot of cool people and technology in china. It seems the Great Firewall runs deep.</p>
<p>Cool, hopefully you can see some longform appear here in the near future! Or this will devolve back into a nature photoblog (I’ll keep that going on my <a href="http://tumblr.com/daiyi" target="_blank" rel="external">tumblr</a>). Either way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://daiyi.co/blog/2016/11/08/I-went-to-IndieWebCamp/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
